{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A holder of this position was exhumed and tried for perjury in the Cadaver Trial. Byzantine governors of the Exarchate of Ravenna once appointed people to this position. Gregory the Great reformed this position, which was supposedly given authority over Western Europe by the Donation of Constantine. In the Great Schism, the holder of this position was excommunicated by the Orthodox Church. For ten points, name this religious position, the head of the Catholic Church.",
      "answer": "Pope or Bishop of Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "Engravings by William Hogarth are thought to be precursors to these works, especially one wherein the city of London is destroyed in 1720 by the South Sea Bubble. A creator of these works used them to popularize the elephant as a symbol for the GOP. One of these created after the Albany Congress shows a snake cut into 8 pieces and was made by Benjamin Franklin. Thomas Nast created, for ten points, what type of parody artworks often published in newspapers to comment on current events?",
      "answer": "political cartoons"
    },
    {
      "question": "This U.S. state’s first constitution had a “whites only” clause. A national park in this state surrounds Mount Mazama, whose caldera filled with water after a prehistoric eruption. A wildlife refuge in this state’s Harney Basin was occupied in 2016 by a group led by Ammon Bundy. The Malheur Wildlife Refuge and Crater Lake are within, for ten points, what Western state whose Willamette Valley was the destination for pioneers traveling a 19th century trail?",
      "answer": "Oregon"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city gained its nickname of “City of Palaces” due to a comment by traveler Alexander von Humboldt. Ten days before this city hosted an Olympic games, a group of students and protesters were killed in its Plaza de las Tres Culturas in the Tlatelolco Massacre. Two American athletes displayed a Black Power salute during the 1968 Summer Olympics in, for ten points, what North American capital city?",
      "answer": "Mexico City"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a story set during this conflict, a child falls asleep while playing with a wooden sword in a forest; later, that deaf and mute boy stumbles upon the corpse of his dead parent. During this war, a character is tricked by a disguised scout into attempting to blow up a transportation line, then hallucinates his escape before being hanged for treason. For ten points, name this setting of Ambrose Bierce’s stories “An Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge” and “Chickamauga.”",
      "answer": "American Civil War"
    },
    {
      "question": "Participants in this event were later caught during a gun battle at the Holbeche House. This plan was exposed in a letter addressed to Lord Monteagle, and it strove to replace the sitting monarch with Elizabeth of Bohemia. Robert Catesby helped coordinate this plan, which was scheduled for November fifth. For ten points, name this plot that attempted to blow up James I and English Parliament, but was thwarted when Guy Fawkes was caught.",
      "answer": "Gunpowder Plot"
    },
    {
      "question": "A “Forum” named after this animal was founded by Phyllis Schlafly to oppose passage of the Equal Rights Amendment. A depiction of this animal on posters was accompanied by the phrase “we do our part;” that blue type of this animal was the logo of the National Industrial Recovery Act. The lunar module of the Apollo 11 mission bore the name of this animal. For ten points, name this animal, whose bald type is the national emblem of the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "eagle",
        "Eagle Forum",
        "blue eagles, descriptions of the Eagle module, bald eagles, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. The non-fictional Battle of the Windmill took place as part of an effort to achieve this action, which was taken by Hunters’ Lodges in the early 19th century. Isaac Brock’s death at Queenston Heights prevented one of these efforts. John Burgoyne repulsed an earlier attempt at this action during the Revolutionary War, during which Richard Montgomery died. For ten points, name this military action, frequently performed by the early United States, which sought to gain more territory to the north.",
      "answer": "the U.S. invading Canada"
    },
    {
      "question": "The name of this practice was inspired by a Richard Outcault character, a bald child who appeared in Hogan’s Alley. That comic strip ran in both the Journal and World, respectively owned by William Randolph Hearst and Joseph Pulitzer, moguls who perfected this practice. Public support for the Spanish-American War was garnered via, for ten points, what questionable journalistic practice that uses anonymous sources, questionable facts, and sensationalist headlines to sell more newspapers?",
      "answer": "yellow journalism"
    },
    {
      "question": "In “Human Bondage,” Spinoza’s 64th proposition notes that the knowledge of this concept is inadequate knowledge and that the human mind could not conceive of this concept if the mind possessed adequate ideas. Skeptical theism is a response to a philosophical “problem” of this concept, first originated logically by Epicurus. In Zurvan theology, Angra Mainyu chose to embody this concept. For ten points, name this moral and ethical concept, often represented in Christian theology by demons and contrasted with “good.”",
      "answer": [
        "evil",
        "word forms and reasonable synonyms, like badness",
        "the Problem of Evil",
        "synonyms of destruction after Angra Mainyu is said",
        "sin and equivalents after Christian is said"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country launched the Christmas Offensive in a war that began with a border skirmish at Wal Wal. One ruler of this country condemned the use of mustard gas in a speech at the League of Nations. The Derg overthrew a ruler of this country in a communist coup, and Italy annexed this African country prior to World War II. For ten points, name this country, once ruled by Menelik II and Haile [”highly”] Selassie, whose capital is Addis Ababa.",
        "answer": "Ethiopia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Menelik II and Haile Selassie both belonged to an Ethiopian dynasty named for this Biblical figure, due to his relationship with the Queen of Sheba. This man is credited with building the First Temple.",
        "answer": [
          "Solomon",
          "Solomonic Dynasty"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this battle, John Gordon noted that he had fought his troops “to a frazzle” and required heavy support from James Longstreet. The winning commander in this skirmish was afflicted with a migraine until he received word that the fighting was over; shortly after, Wilmer McLean’s house served as a meeting place. For ten points, name this Civil War battle that took place on the morning of April 9, 1865, a few hours before Ulysses Grant accepted Robert E. Lee’s surrender, effectively ending the war.",
        "answer": "Battle of Appomattox Court House"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ironically, Wilmer McLean moved his family to Appomattox to avoid the war; his farmland had been the site of this early battle of the war.",
        "answer": "First Battle of Bull Run or First Battle of Manassas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This mountain range was the target of Germany’s Operation Edelweiss in World War II, and its tallest peak was once known as Strobilus. The easternmost end of this mountain range is the Absheron Peninsula. Secessionist republics on the southern slope of this mountain range include Abkhazia and South Ossetia. Mount Elbrus is a part of, for ten points, what mountain chain that runs from the Black Sea to the Caspian Sea, shared by Azerbaijan, Georgia, and Russia?",
        "answer": "Caucasus Mountains"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This federal subject of Russia in the north Caucasus attempted to secede under the name of Ichkeria after the breakup of the USSR. It has its capital at Grozny.",
        "answer": "Chechnya or Chechen Republic"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThiscomposerwroteaTe Deum tocelebratetheTreatyofUtrecht.The“Airandvariations”fromthis composer’s Suite no. 5 for harpsichord is also known as The Harmonious Blacksmith. This man included a largo al siciliana titled “La Paix” in a piece written to celebrate the Treaty of Aix-La-Chapelle. Music for the Royal Fireworks was written by, for ten points, what German-born English Baroque composer who also wrote the oratorio Messiah?",
        "answer": "George Frideric Handel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Handel included bourees and hornpipes in what collection of pieces, written for a concert held for George II on a barge floating on the Thames River?",
        "answer": "the Water Music"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Prior to 594 BC, this city’s ecclesia did not admit thetes, this city’s lowest class. This city’s wealth grew after the discovery of silver at Laurium; Themistocles convinced this city to use that wealth on a new navy, which it promptly used to defeat the Persians at Salamis. The Delian League’s treasury was held in the Parthenon on this city’s Acropolis. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state whose wealth funded broad cultural movements and the birth of democracy.",
        "answer": "Athens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ancient Greek coins were minted in a number of denominations; this most common coin was the approximate value of a day’s wage for a hoplite. The Athenian “owl” was a coin with value equal to four of these coins.",
        "answer": "drachmae"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person prepared a summary of his arguments, the Smalcald Articles, for a defensive alliance known as the Schmalkaldic League. This man, who broke with tradition by marrying Katharina von Bora, was condemned by the bull Exsurge Domine [ex-oor-gay doh-mee-nay] for actions taken after he objected to Johann Tetzel’s sale of indulgences. For ten points, identify this German monk who nailed his 95 Theses to a cathedral door, beginning the Protestant Reformation.",
        "answer": "Martin Luther"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Luther was condemned by Charles V at this 1521 meeting, where Charles issued an edict forbidding anybody to help Luther.",
        "answer": "Diet of Worms"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event led to the end of the 1798 Treaty of Alliance. A woman with a feathered hat has her belongings stuffed into the “national sack” in a depiction of this event, which prompted the Quasi-War. During this event, Pierre Bellamy was chastised by Charles Pinckney, who declared “no, not a sixpence!” For ten points, name this scandal in which American diplomats were asked for a bribe in order to meet with a French diplomat.",
        "answer": "XYZ Affair"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Two of the three American diplomats involved in the XYZ Affair left without ever accomplishing their goal: speaking with this French Foreign Minister.",
        "answer": "Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-P´erigord"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these structures in Rome is named for Cestius. Another of these structures in North America began slumping by 1200 AD; that structure, Monks Mound, was built in Cahokia. An early form of this structure, Etemenanki, was a temple dedicated to Marduk. Sacrifices to Quetzalcoatl were performed on these structures in Aztec territory, and Chichen Itza was a Mayan example of this structure. Ziggurats were terraced examples of, for ten points, what massive ancient religious structures, commonly built in ancient Egypt?",
        "answer": "pyramid"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Many Egyptian pharaohs, including Tutankhamun and Ramesses the Great, were buried in this valley on the West Bank of the Nile.",
        "answer": "Valley of the Kings"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Calvin Coolidge...",
      "prompt": "Name the calvin coolidge......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the governor of what state, where he led from Boston?",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became President after what Republican suffered a cerebral hemorrhage and died in 1923?",
          "answer": "Warren G. Harding"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was succeeded by what President, who got little of the “Roaring Twenties” fun and, instead, the start of the Great Depression?",
          "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
        },
        {
          "question": "Appointed J. Edgar Hoover the head of what agency, a decade before its name change? Old or modern name acceptable.",
          "answer": [
            "Federal Bureau of Investigation",
            "FBI",
            "BOI"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Arbitrated the 1912 “Bread and Roses” strike, put on by members of what “wobbly” union?",
          "answer": "Industrial Workers of the World or IWW"
        },
        {
          "question": "Put down a 1919 strike of what public employees in Boston?",
          "answer": [
            "Police officers",
            "equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed to adequately respond to a 1927 flood of what river?",
          "answer": [
            "Mississippi River",
            "Great Mississippi Flood"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Agreed with what Pennsylvanian banker, his Treasury Secretary, on the benefits of low taxes?",
          "answer": "Andrew Mellon"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Operation Barbarossa",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Former country that Nazi Germany targeted in Barbarossa, on the Eastern Front in Europe.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union or USSR",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "CCCP",
            "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alliance of Germany and Italy that launched the invasion.",
          "answer": "Axis Powers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Nazi Germany that ordered it.",
          "answer": "Adolf Hitler"
        },
        {
          "question": "Genocide of six million people that took place in occupied territories after the invasion.",
          "answer": "Holocaust"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-aggression pact that Germany broke to launch Barbarossa.",
          "answer": "Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Target of Army Group North during the invasion. The siege of this city lasted 872 days.",
          "answer": [
            "Leningrad",
            "St. Petersburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "casus belli of the invasion, a German word that translates as “living space.”",
          "answer": "Lebensraum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Code name for the summer 1942 offensive of Army Group South in the Caucasus, briefly capturing Soviet oil fields.",
          "answer": [
            "Case Blue or Fall Blau",
            "Operation Braunschweig"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Canada",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French-speaking province, home to a movement seeking independence from Canada.",
          "answer": "Qu´ebec"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city where the 2014 Parliament Hill shooting took place.",
          "answer": "Ottawa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Most populous city, once governed by mayor Rob Ford.",
          "answer": "Toronto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Surname of Prime Ministers Pierre and Justin.",
          "answer": "Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "1917 disaster that destroyed a Nova Scotian port and killed thousands.",
          "answer": "Halifax explosion or equivalents"
        },
        {
          "question": "Western oil-producing province that suffered the Fort McMurray wildfire in 2016.",
          "answer": "Alberta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Flat terrace overlooking the St. Lawrence River where opposing generals, Wolfe and Montcalm, died in a 1759 battle.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Plains of Abraham"
        },
        {
          "question": "Canadian Prime Minister who won a Nobel for negotiating an end to the Suez Canal crisis.",
          "answer": "Lester Pearson"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler sought to gain prestige by fighting the War of Devolution against the Triple Alliance. In order to fund his wars against the League of Augsburg and the (20 pts)",
        "Grand Alliance, this monarch employed Jean-Baptiste Colbert to manage his kingdom’s finances. A civil war called the Fronde helped this man expand his power into an absolute monarchy. This man brought much of his nobility to the (10 pts)",
        "palace of Versailles [vair-sigh]. For ten points, name this Sun King who ruled France for over seventy years."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Louis XIV",
        "the Sun King until mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The “bells were ringing out” for this event as “the NYPD choir sing[s] ‘Galway Bay’” in The Pogues’ “Fairytale of New York.” Another song about this event asks “And what have you done?” before commanding “Let’s stop all the fight;” that song parenthetically claims (20 pts)",
        "“War is Over” and is sung by John Lennon, Yoko Ono, and a children’s choir. Bob Geldof organized a 1984 single to raise money for an Ethiopian famine; the title of that song asks (10 pts)",
        "“Do They Know It’s” this holiday. For ten points, name this holiday, also the subject of more traditional songs like “Carol of the Bells” and “Santa Claus is Coming to Town.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Christmas Day and/or Eve",
        "“Happy Christmas War is Over”",
        "“Do They Know It’s Christmas”, and",
        "it if they finish the lyric, because we’re not really going for the title"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A popular movement in this state led to the Supreme Court case of Luther v. Borden and an uprising put down by a militia called by this state’s governor, Samuel Ward King. Thomas Wilson Dorr fought for democratic reform in this state, which was the site of the Great (20 pts)",
        "Swamp Fight and the burning of the Gaspee during the colonial era. In the 1630s, the Narragansett Indians sold the land that would make up this state to (10 pts)",
        "Roger Williams. For ten points, name this U.S. state, the site of Providence Plantation and the smallest U.S. state."
      ],
      "answer": "Rhode Island and Providence Plantations"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1972, dissident poet Pedro Luis Boitel died in one of these events in Cuba. In 1980, one of these events was briefly led by Brendan Hughes; when its demands weren’t met, this event was re-started, and (20 pts)",
        "Provisional IRA member Bobby Sands was the first to die. The World Medical Association declares that attempts to forcefully end these events are considered torture, as has been done at (10 pts)",
        "Guantanamo Bay using IV bags. For ten points, name this event in which a protester refuses nourishment. ANSWER:hunger strike(acceptdescriptions;promptongeneraltermslike“(political)protest;”prompt on descriptions of suicide (attempts)) (5) In 2007, six people were extradited from this country to Bulgaria, where President Georgi Parvanov pardoned them for allegedly infecting 400 children in this country with HIV. From 2014 to 2016, this country’s port city of Derna was under the control of ISIS. This country’s (+) Council of Deputies runs a government that rivals an internationally- recognized government in Tobruk. Christopher (*) Stevens, a former ambassador to this country, was killed in a 2012 attack in Benghazi. For ten points, name this African country led until 2011 by Muammar Gaddafi."
      ],
      "answer": "Libya"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One ruler of this dynasty enlisted the help of the Sea Beggars to capture Brielle but was later assassinated by the Catholic extremist Balthasar Gerard. The Duke of Alba established the Council of Blood to quash a revolt by a (20 pts)",
        "“silent” ruler of this dynasty during the Eighty Years War. A ruler of this dynasty overthrew James I to become king of (10 pts)",
        "England during the Glorious Revolution. William III hailed from, for ten points, what colorfully named royal house of the Netherlands?"
      ],
      "answer": "House of Orange"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The breakdown of this substance was the subject of the 1987 Montreal Protocol. A 1974 paper by Molina and Rowland explains how this compound could be catalytically broken down by high frequency (20 pts)",
        "UV radiation. Each spring, a photochemical reaction depletes this compound in the troposphere over the Earth’s (10 pts)",
        "poles. Trichloroethane and other CFCs create “holes” in the atmospheric layer of, for ten points, what compound, consisting of three oxygen atoms, which protects Earth from the Sun’s radiation?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ozone",
        "O before “oxygen” is read 3"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, defenders were pocketed in the Schnee Eifel [shnay eye-fell] while defending St. Vith, managing to significantly delay the offensive. Heavy fog prevented effective air cover during the beginning of this battle, which was ended when (20 pts)",
        "Patton’s Third Army was able to relieve defending forces. This battle was called Operation Watch on Rhine by its attackers, who were targeting Antwerp. While defending Bastogne [bast-own], General McAuliffe replied (10 pts)",
        "“Nuts!” to a demand of surrender in, for ten points, what World War II battle in the Ardennes, a German attack that caused a namesake shape in the Allied lines?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Bulge",
        "Operation Watch on Rhine before mention"
      ]
    }
  ]
}